okay Mary we are recording and it's good
to see you and talk to you again I
invited you to have a discussion with me
because you're producing and we were
just talking about the fact that you've
released another video today and you're
making a lot of really excellent and
insightful commentary and criticism and
the good sense of the word of criticism
of my work so I thought it would be good
if we could you know talk and we could
discuss some of these issues you raised
and some of the proposals you make and
some of the insights you have so thanks
for thanks for coming on and talking to
me well thank you for your time I was
told by a number of people when I made
my video not the ones today but the last
one that if I that if I put forward
another way of knowing it would be
unacceptable if it did not start with a
piece well well maybe we could start
there then because I want to talk about
the parabolic stuff I think that's very
interesting I I don't know if you've
read any of salad mix eggs theology
because she she does a lot of work on
the role of parable and the role of
metaphor just wrote a book she wrote a
book called speaking in parables and
which I read which is quite good and
another one metaphorical theology which
was also quite good so she made she
makes arguments similar to yours that so
you might find that some I think some
very interesting literature to take not
to take a look at so here's what here's
how I guess I want to start thinking
about that of course we're proposing a
taxonomy and there's no sort of
objective way to decide if a taxonomy is
right or not you have to just decide in
terms of how useful it is and how
effective it is so let me tell you sort
of the the principles by which I was
operating and the distinctions I had in
mind and then what I think about the
parabolic stuff so when I was thinking
about the taxonomy I was thinking about
it in terms of what does it result in
like propositional results and belief
procedural results in
skills respectable results in here now
NASA presence and participatory results
in a sense of belonging
attunement at one man and then each one
also has unlike a normative standard
there's truth power presence right again
one mint and I wanted to keep that
distinct from particular methods of
knowing and what do I mean by a method
so a method of knowing is something like
you know the scientific method there is
historical methods and methods of
knowing of course aren't the same thing
because both the scientific and the
historical method both result in
propositional knowledge you can do of
course different kinds of methods for
training different kinds of skills I can
do Tai Chi for trading martial arts
skills I can learn to swim which trains
a different set of skills so there's
different methods and so what I'm
wondering is is the parabolic a kind of
knowing or is it a method because I'm
not clear what it results in that's
distinct from you know beliefs or skills
or states of consciousness or states of
the self I'm sort of running out of an
inventory of right so before before you
answer let me make one more thing
because I want to make sure that you're
not I'm not miss misrepresenting I do
you think what you're talking about is
important that's why I talked about
McRoberts work at the beginning so this
is not meant to dismiss the phenomena at
all okay the point is whether or not it
should be understood as a kind of
knowing or an important method of
knowing that might be analogous to the
scientific method and give us a way of
acquiring beliefs or skills in ways that
we can't acquire scientifically or
historically or etcetera and why why
there is a little bit of history sort of
behind that proposal of course as people
have been talking for a while about
things like narrative and metabolic ways
sort of not metabolic I'm metaphorical I
confuse parabolic and metaphorical
uh you know narrative and metaphorical
methods for gaining new beliefs which is
still from would for me would still
count as a kind of propositional knowing
okay so let me take it let me take a
stab at it okay okay so the question is
what is it no is it knowledge or is it
hey
or is it is it a kind of knowing or is
it a method a minute method for getting
a particular domain right or so I can
okay so I would say that I would
question whether it's a method because
I'm tired of what I said about the way
that children seem to do it
automatically my question was not my my
point about it was not that the child
does it as a method but that it seems to
it seems to presuppose that there's
something the child knows already so not
so it's not in making the it's not in
making the metaphor as a as a as a way
of as a losing that word again that he
said as a method but rather what is
lying underneath it what does the child
know that is being expressed so what a
child does that does that makes sense
what I'm saying I think so let me
understand so the is the issue then that
you weren't so obviously people use
metaphor and we use metaphor to change
belief and so for me that would count as
propositional knowing although there's
some maybe prospective of shifting going
on in there and that's that I think that
that's fine but what you saying is what
you were interested in was the
possibility that children don't have to
be sort of taught this it's sort of an
innate ability is that the idea we're
getting to well that it's an expression
of a some kind of knowledge it's an
expression of some kind of knowledge but
it it's not any of the kinds of
knowledge except you might push back and
say well it's maybe it's participatory
knowledge because the child is embedded
within the family is already
participating it
well it's sort of whatever yeah what I'm
thinking about the the the reason I
called it parabolic is it has to do with
this setup of relationships right and I
talked about how when we set those
relationships up we collapsed the
combinatorially explosive nature of the
of the different ways that we can that
we can compare to things like the
example I used was the child comparing
the knife and fork and spoon to show you
know water mother baby that is
combinatorially explosive you know if
you were just to go the knife and the
father what are the ways they're like
one of the way sir this is coming from
what you said right one of the ways
they're like what are the ways they're
just similar it's common to totally
explosive how does the child collapse
that all that comment oral explosive to
the point of saying father mother baby
and I'm saying that it has to do with
with relationship okay so let me let me
try I'll ask you a question and how is
that any different than Rutherford using
the relationships within the solar
system to explain the structure of the
atom right so here's the Sun at the
center the planet's orbit here's the
nucleus at the center and the electrons
orbit so you're mapping relations in
fact that that's Dedra get nurse sort of
theory of what we do in metaphor we map
a system of relations from one domain
onto another okay and when why I bring
up that example is obviously because
it's clearly within scientific
theorizing and secondly it would be
implausible to me that you you had sort
of any innate knowledge of the atom or
something like that right and that and
that is and that is kind of the that is
kind of gets to my point that that there
is something that the child knows
innately okay that is being expressed
now is there something in a innately
knowledge being expressed when someone
guys says well the atom is like a solar
system there might be that might go too
I read your paper are you work about the
geometric shapes really don't work that
you're looking at you're looking at
geometric relationships and you're able
to map them one on to the other
yeah but that's different from from that
seems to me different now if the child
Ward ten years old and we're in a
classroom and they were having a social
studies lesson about families and for
some reason the teacher pulled out a
knife as well then the child's being
taught something similar the whole thing
with Adam and the solar system but this
child seems to know something that is
being expressed when the child says you
know mommy daddy mommy baby about the
knife fork and spoon and just like with
my daughter's they seem to be expressing
the knowledge like when they said you
know doc dogs are boys and cats are
girls and these are all dogs or boys all
cats are girls you know them on that and
then people in the comments under that
video that I did that he talked about
knowing that when they were little like
I think Sevilla King said I knew that
when I was 2 years old was 2 years old I
knew all cats were boys at all I mean
all dogs were boys and all cats were
girls
what did so my question is then what did
she know what kind of knowledge is
expressed by that no I'm not talking
about the expression itself but there's
something no so that's a different
question so let's shift off there then
so if the issue isn't primarily sort of
metaphorical mapping which i think is an
important ability I talked about this
and like I think like the second episode
so right that ability I think is one of
the things that comes gives us emerges
in the Upper Paleolithic transition and
I would say the ability to do metaphor
is probably an 8 whether or not specific
metaphors are innate we can come back
to that at least the ability to do the
mapping but the if the question is
innate nurse then it seems to me then
there are many there are many kinds of
potentially innate forms of knowledge if
that's what we're talking about so for
example I mean you know Lewis Carroll
famously argued that I can't teach you
how modus ponens works I can't teach you
if P then Q P therefore Q because what
would I possibly use to teach you
I need the rule in order to teach you
that rule so the rule is unlearn about
so it has to be an eight or a sense of
contradiction like how could I teach you
contradiction it has to be an innate
ability and this is kind of you know an
idea that goes back to Plato yeah we
come with a lot of knowledge that must
be an eight because if we don't have
that innate knowledge we can't actually
explain learning and then a recent
version of that of course is Chomsky
right the idea that we come with a
universal grammar that allows us to
learn any particular language so chill
you don't have to teach children
language at all you teach if to teach
some literacy you don't have to teach
them to speak you just have to expose
them to speech and then they will learn
it and so that to me then seems to me to
be sort of a different a different thing
we're talking about because it seems to
me again that what I could say is well
it seems to me that there are probably
propositional procedural perspectival
and participatory forms of any
acknowledge that innate knowledge isn't
a separate kind of knowing it's what
we're saying is this is a knowing that
isn't is not learned but again what does
it result in does it result in well
results in a belief or a skill or
explosive well it so I'm glad we shifted
off of metaphor because I don't think
metaphor explains how we collapse
combinatorial explosion it actually
presupposes that we can do relevance
realization on tour so if the question
then this is good I think we're making
good progress together if the question
is is one and this is plato's answer and
I think Chomsky's answer is the question
is part of how we
constrained combinatorial explosion and
B relevance realization hardwired in if
you'll allow me that horrible metaphor
because we're not really doing anyways
but that's the common language we use
for it these days is that one of the
ways I think that's definitely the case
I think in fact I so I am deeply
critical of the opposite view the
opposite view is John Locke's view that
were tabula rasa that so I think if
you're tabula rasa then you just face
Plato's Minos paradox if you don't have
any right if you don't have anybody
that's just too combinatorial explosive
you can't even get started with any
learning whatsoever and I think Locke's
four principles of Association are too
weak to explain all of learning I've
just been teaching a course on all of
that so if the question is do we have
innate knowledge and does it contribute
significantly to our capacity for
reducing combinatorial explosion yeah I
think so
I think and I think there's lots of
stuff I think you know the ability to
walk as an example of procedural that's
also that's an eight children basically
just if you leave children alone and let
them practice they'll walk on their own
it's not really true to say they learn
how to walk right is they you said they
express it it comes out um and so I
think that's like I agree with that I
just don't quite see that I don't think
it belongs to the same taxonomy as the
four peas that's that's what I'm trying
to say okay so let me let me ask you
then just a question when the child does
that yes you know or takes three blocks
and you know makes a little family out
of them and what what does what is it
the child knows and what kind of
knowledge of your four peas would you
say that is oh well I think that what
the child is knowing is exactly what you
said it is which is a system of
relations between concepts and that's
that's prototypical Willie wet produce
that's what propositional knowledge is
right you have various concepts like
there's a system of relationship between
mom and dad which are concepts
then between fork and spoon or which
which example forked knife right I want
to get it right let's see I'm not a very
good kid I guess
so I mean and we and and I think we do
have that ability to do that mapping
between now an interesting thing you
might be saying is the mapping itself is
not an inferential process I think
that's I think that's right
I think that's right it's propositional
either because the child cannot the
child cannot for it so you saying we
have propositional knowledge before
we're able to articulate it articulate
propositions of course we do of course
we do think about you know so right the
child clearly knows that cats and dogs
are both animals right because that's
why she doesn't ever ever you'll never
see the kid link we you know group
together a cat in a chair and they
somehow belong together in the category
right and so in fact there's good
research Scott OTT Rinna's showing that
one of the innate things we might have
and mithran talks about this is we might
come with an innate capacity sort of to
distinguish between living things
nonliving things and artifacts and so we
don't have to learn that we have some
basic machinery that helps us because if
you look for example across different
cultures at how they categorize living
things they tend to have this
hierarchical structures that are the
same now obviously what people put in
the categories are doing a different
depending on the animals in the
environment but the logical structure of
how they category categories animals is
very similar and Scott action did a lot
of work to show that and it strikes me
as very plausible that we come sort of
evolutionarily prepared to identify in a
kind of very precise way living things
and that seems to me to be you know
taxonomy ZAR sort of prototypical
instances of propositional knowing right
yes that would explain what you just
said that would explain
in your when you were doing the work on
the squares and circles
yeah the plants and animals yeah you put
plants and animals almost as though they
were opposites but people people plug
this circle from a plant as well as for
the animals so did you notice that yeah
I do not offices cuz they're both alive
yeah and it's yeah so yeah it's
interesting where the mappings are like
beyond 50% because that's where it
matters because it 50 it's gonna be my
mapping 50% cuz there's two things yeah
is when you're when you're up sort of
beyond 65 to 70 that it's interesting
everything below that yeah I think
you're right it just it doesn't reflect
anything yeah that's a good point but it
was also like it's also interesting how
you know we do some of it a lot of
people are agreeing on these mappings
well you know that you know living and
dead with circle being alive and swear
being dead and things like that which
again there is again here let me point
out something really interesting to you
when when you when people people agree
to that mapping but they don't find the
metaphorical equivalent I think I sent
you that paper too right yeah yes they
don't find a metaphorical equivalent
it's all intelligible to them so that
that says to me that the mapping yeah or
if you you can't say to somebody you
know that's really circular as a way of
saying it's really alive it just doesn't
work for them right work for people and
so that's what I mean when I think that
the mapping ability the ability to map
these relations is is probably at least
some of it is probably an important
innate function and then what I think is
really interesting what I what you
brought up is though because this is
what you went on to do is the way that
I'm hesitating to my work I can hear
philosophers in my head right now but
the way in which innate capacity that
innate sin
if you'll allow me that word might be
something that comes to particular
expression within religious experience
because this was all part of your
overall essay on personal experience
right I thought that was a very
interesting idea well it was an answer
to you saying when we were talking about
whether God is personal and you talked
about the ambiguity yeah one of the
things you said is that between our
knowledge of a person and the ground of
being
the differences and the stories are
combinatorially explosive if and that's
where I use the thing about the fish in
the bird right so like the difference
between a fish and a bird is coming to
are like explosive the similarity is
coming to explosive but if I say to you
bird is doing as fishes to blank you
it's like a fin yeah yeah collapses that
comment are like you know looking at the
relationship and set up between the
things instead of looking at the things
collapses that combinatorially explosive
nature of the similarities and
differences could what do you think
about that okay well there's two things
to say about that first I think there's
an important idea there and this goes
back to the point I made earlier though
because again sorry I don't want the
number of relations you can find within
a thing and write you right again
think about think about the problem this
way Mary Henley brought it up how do you
decide which thing to use as your source
for let's say we're Rutherford and we've
got all this data about about the atom
and we're trying to figure what should
we map it on to well it's
combinatorially explosive so I map it
onto a clock a table by Mike map it onto
a river right and so she says you get to
this problem because if you say well
what you need
I need something to constrain what I
search my search so I'll zero in on the
right thing but that's just the problem
again of zeroing in on the relevant
information so
I think what I was suggesting to you is
that I wanted to know it's a good point
you're making all your points are good I
don't mean it that way I'll point out an
agreement with and a point that I'm
challenging the point I'm challenging
right now is a is your ability to map
relations actually presupposes a lot of
relevance realization because in order
to get the two things paired together
that you're then going to draw the
systematic relationship to right you
have to have done a lot of relevance
realization in the first place okay now
what you're you should say to me is but
some of these pairings seem very natural
to me
well what I want to say something a
little different which is yes when I'm
creating the analogy I'm you know I
already think I already know things
about fish and I already know things
about birds nets and their you know
their body shape and their the function
of their limbs etc that makes me able to
make the analogy start agreeing with you
there but that's not the same thing as
when I say say it and someone else
responds instantly with the answer in
other words if I'm sitting down trying
to think of the analogy yes I'm I'm
using does that make sense what I'm
saying you know no let me let me say it
back to make sure I'm understanding you
so you you're agreeing with me that
generating the metaphor in the first
place is requires relevance realization
but once you have made that mapping it's
a powerful way for me to help you but
let's say I'm the speaker of the
metaphor
so I somehow I'm waving my hands now I
somehow solve relevance realization
combinatorial explosion I come up with a
good metaphor but when I pass that
metaphor on to you that really helps you
very rapidly collapse the
combinatorially explosive space is that
what you're saying yes yes I agree with
that see so as a cognitive scientist I
had to I have to pay attention to the
first problem because that's the problem
trying to give a
computer or an AI the ability to
generate and recognize metaphors in the
first place I agree that what we can do
is we can we can collapse combinatorial
explosion for people through the use of
metaphor in very very powerful ways
there's many ways in which we can help
each other
collapse combinatorial explosion so what
what did you want me to take note about
that because I wanted to apply that I
wanted to apply that to what you said
about the difference between our
knowledge of my person and the ground of
being for you to say there may be a
common literally explosive number of
ways in which the ground of being is
personal would be a combinatorial
explosive number of ways in which the
ground of being is impersonal all right
then I then what I said was but if we
map relationships we can collapse a
combinatorial explosive that
combinatorial explosive number of of
things so that that's when I said if God
the Father is to God the Son in if God
the Father is to God the Son as John is
to his son in some way solely that
combinatorially explosive from nature
has collapsed and of course I'm my
argument is that it collapses in the
direction of the personal you know you'd
have to come up with your own set of
metaphors for collapsing it towards the
impersonal but that's that's the case
that I'm making because that was like
that original right so I I agree I think
I'm if I understand you correctly I do
think that one of the ways in which we
can collapse the combinatorially let's
we agreed on this last time it was
helpful for both of us so I'm making a
request that we could we can have this
common term of ultimate reality right oh
yeah yeah I'm sorry that's why
and so the idea is and the idea which
you you know I argued for that that
reality is combinatorial explosive and I
do you think we can collapse it we can
collapse the combinatorial explosion and
I even agree with you that and I think
I've argued this that there's that we're
going to inherently have to rely on
metaphor and symbolic things in order to
make that collapse work that I am in
agreement with and the fact that people
would find uh I wanted to make sure I
don't you use my adjectives confusing
that people would find metaphors to
persons personally relevant there we go
I didn't I didn't I didn't screw up I
think that also strikes me as very
plausible because I would agree with you
that we're sort of wired for attachment
relationships and living things and
perhaps even you know as mammals where
there might be a parental child thing
that's innate for us and so that might
give a kind of I want to use like I
don't want this please this isn't meant
to be dismissive but it could make it
that could be easy that could be easy
for people right to do that
it could be accessible very x okay
that's better i like that better that
could be very accessible for people both
in both senses individually that I can
make sense to it for myself and also
it's easy for me to communicate to you
how I've made sense of it so I
acknowledge all of that I think that's
all alright
and and I think this is convergent I
think maybe you'll disagree but I think
this is a conversion with Paul's
argument Paul Van de clay right that we
need to because of the nature of reality
we need to bring a spirit of finesse to
it rather than a spirit of geometry and
that he says tends to orient us towards
personal symbols rather than impersonal
ones so I think so I'm trying to I'm
trying to represent your argument as
fairly as possible and where I'm in
agreement with it I guess the issue for
me then is
that doesn't seem to be an exclusive
property of personal symbols so there
are a lot of impersonal symbols of
ultimate reality that also collapse the
combinatorial explosion yeah and seemed
to go towards again very plausibly
innate things like the fact that we come
plausibly innate with an ability to
Gestalt holes and you know and then so
you can think of platonist as metaphor
of the one right and and think about how
much we invoke this notion and whenever
we're trying to explain something we we
talked about how it's whoa it's one how
its unified right
and that or or two towards Paul's point
does the spirit of finesse require
personal metaphors no I don't think so
I practice Tai Chi Chuan as you know and
Taoism and this is very much the art of
finesse and the point of it isn't just
to get you know physical finessed the
point of it is to give me a
participatory sense of the DAO and so
well I argue what well I agree with you
I don't argue with you I agree with you
that the metaphors do the collapse and
there might be an innate basis to them
it seems to me I can make an equivalent
equivalent argument for that I have
impersonal metaphors that also collapse
and are also based on innate mechanisms
well and I think I would respond to that
by saying that I agree I don't think
that the impersonal metaphors are in any
way illegitimate because I think that
the personal can include the impersonal
um I guess the question would be can the
impersonal include the personal so that
might be something to that might just be
something that you know think about
because I could because I don't think
you know we have this um you know catyph
attic spirituality the
Christianity which goes beyond the
identity of God as any fitting into any
categories that we have at all right and
you know I'm very respectful of that so
so it I guess one of the reasons we're
coming around to this is getting back to
all of your great work on the meaning
crisis but the question
the big question kind of out there that
you could of whether Christianity had
like the resources don't know what does
it have does it have the resources to to
deal with the meaning crisis and of
course my big argument I'm making is yes
it does and you know I'm trying to bring
some of the thinking Christian thing
here to questions you have that you have
you know laid out there so well so
that's right no I I want to respond to
that because I think that's a very good
point you're making
first of all Mary I want to remind you
that I've never claimed a foreclosure
argument I've never I do that and I make
that very very clear you know this is
this is kind of like there's an urgent
problem and we have to sort of place our
bets as to where we're gonna place our
resources and that's why that's all I've
tried to make it clear that's always the
style of the argument I'm making now
what we're I'm a little bit stronger but
but I think you don't fall into this
camp there's people that are sort of
committed to you know a two worlds
mythology and a strictly personalistic
mythology for Christianity because I do
think that is I don't think that has the
resources but what I see you doing
frequently and what I say cheap cheapy
doing right is you guys are I don't know
I don't I'm not I don't want to get you
in the hot water about saying something
that might make you look like a heretic
or something like that
but it seems to me like you guys are
trying to craft a different vocabulary
some from the phenomenology I mean it
isn't rotzinger doing that to some
degree - yes von Hildebrand yeah number
of Catholic theologian stood I would say
early in the 20th century are in the
twentieth century now they could no
longer as I put it in vogue Thomas
Aquinas and its people to stand up and
salute yes it wasn't it wasn't doing the
work that that it had once done which I
think you know not just I'm not being
dismissive of Aquinas I think it was
important work what he what Thomas
Aquinas said was important and during
training of the of the intellectual you
know strata of Europe was really on hand
the whole bringing of Aristotle into the
discourse but it's kind of reached sort
of reached an end where we've maybe my
mind it not from a personal standpoint
because I would say that just anyone
coming up and learning philosophy is
gonna get a lot of Aquinas I agree I'm
not saying it from that standpoint but
I'm saying that from culturally yeah
having that kind of status and just have
it anymore
and so there isn't there isn't a desire
to find new ways to talk about these
things and it's not it's not a matter of
it's not a matter of heresy or being or
that I would fall into heresy or be
accused of ever see anything like that I
don't have any fears and I don't have
any position to famous or anything so
but I I do think of phenomenology is key
and now I know the personalism of john
paul ii i don't know you know like his
theology of the body and all of that
work that he did so okay so in my latest
this kind of brings us up to when i did
today the video released today so i want
to talk about about meaning cuz you know
yeah you keep distracting me i'm
supposed to be doing Ratzinger i keep
talking about your stuff instead
but you talk about meaning and I think
this is part this was part of your
conversation they had with Sweeney also
part of the conversation you had with my
son stock and yo.hannes
you know yeah yeah yeah yeah our and
when talking about if they're wrong
teams I'm just learning johannes his
name it great guy by the way great guy
I'm a really lucky yeah I loved I love
the conversation you'll see how many
things I tied into it in my video but I
want to focus on the sake of meaning
because what occurred to me when you
were talking about meaning and they also
mentioned taking making was part of the
conversation with guy and Johannes right
people make things and what do people
how does that connected I talked a lot
about that in my video today letting my
appetite for but this part about meaning
we just talked about the fact that
meaning is not just like having a
purpose like set a goal and you'll have
meaning but it's being connected to
something larger so that got me thinking
about okay but meaning goes in two
directions this is like this opponent
processing stuff and the emaan eminence
and emergence right right not just that
you meet you you mean something to
something larger so your you haven't you
know what your embedded in a structure
larger than yourself that um you matter
to it yeah you matter that's the word I
wanted you matter to it right but it's
also that things matter to you yes these
are interrelated yes
the more that thing the more that you
matter the more that things matter to
you the lesson you matter the less of
things matter to you yes I agree
so the illustration I used was of a
hunter right a hunter goes out and
gets food brings it back for his
community and I was listening in the Joe
Rogan talking to a guy that was a hunter
for both hunters and they talked about
the great satisfaction and the great
feeling of being a provider of being
able to bring back the game you know cut
it up give it to their friends and their
friends send them pictures of barbecue
grill and just a set the feeling that
I've provided for my family I provided
for my community and how how deeply that
touched them and that's how I was
thinking okay
like the Hunter had matters to his
community more he matters to his
community the more his hunting is going
to matter to him yes yes and the more
his hunting matters to him the more he
matters to his community yeah I know so
what I tied that in with is the that
this is this gets back to your several
conversations ago that we had when we
talked about worship right all right so
I realized that see what I did when I
was talking to you about worship is I
use the two mystic atomistic explanation
you know it's the virtue of justice and
this little applied to our relationship
to God and that I didn't not that did
not strike you that did not like that
you didn't go oh wow yes there's
something inadequate about saying it
that way so I want to try to say it
another way which is that the human the
you know man I'm using man generically
is a priest that is his status until you
know within the cosmos okay because he
because he mediates between different
levels of reality okay so the hunter is
gathering you know or a farmers
gathering something from down here
bringing it up and then giving it to the
higher order to the community sure all
right so that's and that in itself is a
priestly act so that worship is this
mediation between these different levels
of reality the blessing bringing the
blessing down from above and dispersing
it out or gathering from below and then
sending it up above and that that is
what that is what worship is it and one
of the illustrations I use I went back
because I use the hunting illustration
several times in in my video today was
that for example the hunters have to get
hunting licenses right from their
community that's get a hunting license
and then the feast I pay for the hunting
licenses are using conservation so
they're bringing the blessing of the
higher order is mediated through them to
the to the lower order to the you know
but that that point that human point of
sitting there as the mediator between
the different levels is do you think
that means to be a priest and that is
like the role of man and the cosmos is
to do that thing to mediate between the
different levels I like this so let's
talk about this because you're right
that it was more impressive to me than
the the two mystic representation so the
idea of mediation between levels
ontological levels and that being an
important feature of human beings I
think that's important and I like this
idea
because the idea that mattering to
something is a reciprocal relationship
with are internalizing an order so both
of these both of these contribute to
meaning in life one is right that the
sense of mattering to a overarching
thing and the other which I think I
think this is what your hunter analogy
is doing is also that I can internalize
that I can take that order and I take it
in and it gives me intelligibility
and so that's why making sense is also a
significant predictor of meaning in life
so if I've matter to some
thing but I can't internalize it right
into me
then it doesn't it doesn't contribute as
much meaning in life to me as if I can
internalize it
so yes the internalization in the sense
that you are you are composed of
different levels to see this is
happening internally yes I totally agree
I think yeah as well as externally that
but you know when people don't have
meaning they will not just say I don't
matter they'll also say nothing matters
to me it's goes both ways and it's and
the two things are really joined yes and
and and that's I tried to sort of get at
that notion with the notion of trans
javadi it's both the way things are
relevant to us
that's the internalization direction and
the way in which we're relevant to
things right and so yeah I totally agree
with that and the idea that again this
is something that we don't just think it
goes into the very structure the way we
relate to the different levels within
ourselves
I like that Augustinian analogy that
sort of the levels of the psyche you
know mirror that the relationship
between us and a higher order I think I
think that makes sense to me so oh very
platonic it's yeah it's very much an
anarchic way it's basically what affords
an agog a right and so I agree with that
and then the idea that human beings have
a important role not shared with other
organisms because they are mediators
between I don't know like to call them
the order of the ontological orders that
strikes me as very plausible - so is
that what you mean I worship because I
see the mediation and I get it and I get
that the mediation is deeply a kind of
and I kind of enacted symbolism and it's
about you know the - getting getting
there the loop formed
in life mattering and internalizing I
get all that but like what makes it and
I get that like I said I think it has it
could have a sacred import to people a
sacral import to them precisely because
it has to do with sort of fun the
fundamental connection they have to
themselves in the internalization and
the connection to reality that they have
in in the mattering so I get all that
but what's the specific connection to
worship well the worship is it's it's
the it's the same thing on a different
level so like I talked about the Hunter
going getting the animal bringing me
back to the community okay so the
community is the higher order the
environment is the low order and the
Hunter sitting in the middle or you can
use the example like we have in the in
the mass we have gathered together the
elements which is you know the bread and
the wine which is you know from the
environment and then brought it in to
the church and then through the prayers
of the priest it is made into the body
and blood of Christ and then it is
offered to God so it's offered to that
higher level so it's the same it's it's
that priestly action again that
mediation between the different levels
and and also is bringing down the
blessing of God and then that so it's
not just a one-way street
the priesthood is not a one-way street
it's not just offering to God it's also
bringing the blessing of God down to the
community in the same way that the
hunter you know to make the analogy that
the hunter is by paying his fee
contributing to the conservation so
bringing a blessing of the whole
community or the state or whatever you
want to whatever that higher level is
down into the environment so is are you
saying that worship is a particular
species of the genus
so let me let me be clear with an
example so let's say I'm doing Tai Chi
one of my favorite examples and of
course I am right I'm trying to connect
to the environment I'm trying to sort of
matter and fit to my environment right
the DAO I'm trying to conform to the Dow
right and the Dow of course is much
beyond me but of course I'm also
internalizing the Dow and I'm
experiencing that in the front you know
the phenomena of Chi right and so and
that of course is you know it it
energizes me it provides me with the
insight I get into the flow State so I
feel right I don't mean anything I'm
gonna use your word and please don't be
offended
I feel blast in that sense when I'm
receiving that and I feel like also that
I'm right that I'm connecting to
something much larger to myself and I
feel like I'm mediating between my
internal personal self and a larger
order of what's real would you call that
worship I would call that I would
certainly call I would not want to put a
definition on what you do that that you
are not comfortable with but I would say
that that is an exercise of priesthood
okay I would say that in other ways too
like for example when you go to the
library or research your you're taking
from this broader wider a community of
scholars right and then you take that in
you filter it go through yourself then
you distribute it to community of
students you're right so that's that's
the same thing and then from your
community of students you gather some
around you or some close to you who will
do research themselves and then
contribute back up to that yep
so I see the
like a very fundamental aspect of what
human beings are and so now when I went
into my into my video I talked about
what led me to thinking about this is in
in Catholic theology we say that Christ
has three offices priest king and
prophet hmm and and that all of and all
of the baptized participate in all the
offices of Christ but Christ is also the
last item he is man he is the you know
the archetypal man human being and so
that means that that atom man
generically also participates in those
offices or had those offices so what I
said in my video is that you look at the
history of man we see a perversion of
those offices we see that though instead
of bringing down the blessing of God and
gathering the all of creation to praise
God man instead embarked on a you know a
mission of Craig's civilization on the
blood of his brothers which we see with
Cain the story King Mabel right there at
the beginning and Donham perverted the
kingship the Dominion by tyranny and you
know slavery and all of those things
perverted the office of profit by
instead of speaking the truth speaking
you know the Oracles of God instead you
know perverting the truth and lying and
deceit and all of those things but that
Christ Christ comes and he purifies our
participation in those offices he shows
us how to participate in them correctly
and he does that by by uniting the
opposites so he is the priest and the
victim he is the king and a servant and
he is the logos of God the Word of God
but he's also the baby who cannot speak
in the silent lamb so by uniting those
opposites
he gives us that
he gives he trains us in those offices
correctly which none of us are doing
right but you know he does off way to
Jerry that was beautiful I was a
beautiful articulation thank you for
sharing that
so let me see like I get it so you're
saying given sort of the meaning-making
structure of human beings or the meaning
cultivation as I prefer to say it all
right that there's these three offices
that typify are essential to human
though you said priest and king and
prophet and that what that's what Christ
does at least symbolically is right give
us a way of sort of reframing to use my
language those by sort of combining if
you'll allow me breaking frame and
making frame he he gives us the little
baby that breaks a frame right but then
he's also the logos which is to get us
to expand to a bigger frame he breaks
the frame of the tyrant king by being
the suffering servant but then also
expands right to a different idea of
what it is to be a king by leading you
know the transformation of the world
rather than just a country and and so I
I think this is a very powerful argument
for the the what do I want to say here
you need to say this more Mary because
what you're doing exactly the kind of
thing I'm talking about you're going
back and you're trying to we language
these symbols in a way that connects up
with you know the machinery that's being
revealed about human beings in cognitive
science and that's a powerful argument
you made for why Christianity I hope you
take this as something positive why
Christianity could be so powerful and
persuasive for individuals as opposed to
you know the idea that you know people
are Christians just because they're sort
of believing what they're told and stuff
like that I think what you just did
there was really good I realize like I
think it's good I think it's good well
good so okay so let's see well I sort of
want to put a pin in it I guess is what
I'm saying like this is your without you
and also just all of the conversations
that I've been listening to it
I mean besides you in crisp abanda clay
but also like some conversations and joe
rogan which sometimes you know the
language on its podcast is like it's a
90 by wheelhouse and I have to so I have
to I have to do a lot of mental bleeping
when I'm listening to Joe Rogan but and
also like Eric points Weinstein and
different things like that so I think
all of these you know I couldn't have
pulled this together without all of that
in which I think it's there's something
special that is going on here I think so
too
I think so too I just I'd like I said I
like that as an example of trying to to
reformulate Christian mythos in a way
that makes it I'm struggling to not be
just to Dominion it makes it deeply
functional for people as opposed to just
a set of claims what I'm saying is
you're transforming the mythos into
something that will itself become
transformative for people rather than
just transmitting doctrine that's what
I'm trying to put my finger on right
right because I could see when I had had
that conversation with you and I talked
about worship and I what I stated was
doctrine doctrinal and it was too
permissive but I could see and then and
I've heard people say for this in my in
my video I've heard people say you know
even we talked about that weird we ought
to worship God or that you know God is
deserving of worship and people say
things like oh why you God is just like
somebody did Suzy go you have to keep
stroking you know that it comes across
like that that's what it is that it's
just we have to constantly tell God how
great he is otherwise he gets depressed
or something
narcissist of all times and so I had to
and tying it in phenomenologically and
tying in to just to life you know to the
things that we're doing every day show
and this is why I think I think this
gets us out of the to world mythology I
might be wrong about that but you have
to tell me because once it ties into
things like you know gardening and
hunting and making you know making
things and ordinary work that people do
doesn't that get us out of the to world
thing well I think it might I have to
think about that question Mary I don't
I'm not confident that I could answer it
right here right now I let so and that's
what I mean if I'm being a little bit
hesitant the way that you are
reconfiguring transformation in terms of
you know functional processes that
people can engage in and enact rather
than relying on a particular
metaphysical picture that they have to
adhere to that seems to me to I'll say
this it seems to me to be definitely on
the right track yes pondering well I
mean I want you speaking for myself and
I imagine others I want you to keep
doing what you're doing
and I think it's very interesting yeah
like I want to think about that question
you ask me it's a good question it's a
very good question
the the the seekers the way what I like
about this is I can see what you're
talking about and I can see how a lot of
it is integrated with like I said with
sort of a cognitive science perspective
on meaning making and transformation and
things like that that's why I tried to
throw in that extra bit about the frame
breaking in the frame making so with
Jesus Jesus is representing sort of like
an attentional scaling was please don't
don't take this wrong way he's
representing like an intentional scaling
mechanism that helps us you know we
cover the the sort of optimal grip on
kingship and priesthood and prophecy
that I think is really cool yes don't
ask you a question about this gets back
to the child things a minute because
when you do all this work about the
shapes very interesting have you done
any work about and you talk about pre
metaphorical understanding work on
relationship family relationships and
metaphors using family relationships
I haven't Mary Douglas has done quite a
bit of work on that and she talks about
various domains that are natural sources
natural symbols like the body is one so
there's of course tons we do you know
the body of Christ right we so we we do
all kinds of body metaphors and I mean
we even use the word familiar
we've familial metaphors or of course
quite significant and I think the first
one
to the fact that we are innately
embodied and the second one I think goes
towards the fact that we are innately
mammalian and we are and we especially
as prime especially the primates we are
we deeply depend on attachment
relationships for not only our survival
which we do but also for our coming into
personhood you know so so I take it that
her argument is there are certain things
that are going to be in natural symbols
to us because they are deeply grounding
of our of our cognition and our
personhood and they're always available
to us in some fashion so that makes them
a sort of a natural source or what she
quite means by natural is a little bit
unclear but you can at least get what
she's talking about I think intuitively
okay so so I'm wondering what happens to
people's cognitive machinery fake isms
in mind when there is I mean we do know
that people suffer terribly yep children
suffer terribly when there's disruption
that family like being embedded within a
family might be as important as being in
a body oh yeah I think I think it is I
do I do people you think that's true now
of course there's lots of cultural
historical variations on what a family
is all right and so I don't want to say
that ours is sort of the the the
universally prescribed type or something
like that I think that's true because
you sorry there's there's a weird thing
banging around my head might make a
colleague and good friend Jeff McDonald
he teaches relationship psychology at U
of T here
and he basically says and so you'll see
why I was sort of smiling a little bit
he says that attachment theory is the
way the truth and the life
of understanding romantic relationships
if you want to know why people get into
the romantic relationships they do or
even the friendships they do you what
you do is you look at attachment theory
so attachment theory is the different
ways in which children and parents are
attached they can be securely attached
anxiously attached avoidant he attached
and then what he's and he's got a lot of
evidence an argument to support this
what you can see is that pattern plays
out in a powerfully through people's
lives in ways that they're often only
really vaguely aware of it's and and so
this is again the you know the kind of
stuff I try to point to when I talk
about the machinery of the self as
opposed to just the machinery of
consciousness or cognition because these
processes by which we form our romantic
and our friendship relationships of
course ways in which we are also
simultaneously forming our identity and
so the attachment relationships you have
to your parents and to some degree your
siblings right deeply inform the kind of
existential modes you'll get into and
the kind of self you will turn out to be
and that's why you know trauma and
violence within the family is deeply
deeply disruptive of people in really
comprehensive manners right so I'm
wondering how and you would think that
the societal disruption of family and of
young people forming families is
connecting what the meaning Christ
problem but Mary ever stuck actually has
you know how the West really lost God
well have you read this book no but I
Fred did she write Adam and Eve after
the pill I don't know
I don't know her work in general I only
know this one book her basic argument is
that there's a very strong correlation
between the the rise of the disbelief in
God if that's the way to put it and the
breaking down of stable family
structures yes so and and this makes
sense right we can't because again if
you cannot connect two perspectives
beyond you that you are willing to
internalize that will seriously truncate
your ability to make the kinds of
connections that you see sort of as
central to religious and spiritual life
well in his in his encyclical fides said
rot you John Paul the second talked
about faith as preceding preceding
reason hmm and he said it he said it
like this he said that faith is the it's
the original position of the human being
and he's quoted a psalm that said you
have made me to trust at my mother's
breast yeah Erickson talked about that
to the developmental psychologist so so
what you're talking about okay so this
gets me to another question because I
have talked to some about marriage and
you know family life and one of the
things that questions that I had when
you look at your religion you look at
you are
I shouldn't even call it you are let me
just say because I know I know that puts
you in a position you don't want to be
as they're your founding something so to
say is not a religion okay what what is
it that would ground within that ground
the sacredness of family life and the
sacredness of the commitments of members
of the family to one another
is like in through or the you know I'm
not I know that there are ways that this
is done in other religions like in
Hinduism and Buddhism as well because
obviously they have marriages - yeah
it's not but I'm not I'm not clear on
how their marriage
um commitments are connected with their
religion I'm sure they are but I know of
course within Judaism and Christianity
we have the concept of the Covenant of
the marriage covenant the covenant being
the kind of an agreement that forms a
family brings people into family
relationship like adoption or marriage
and that being you know that there are
sacred oaths connected with connecting
with forming a family in the in marriage
what in the religion that is not a
religion what would be the how is that
grounded how is that sacredness of
family life grounded in your conception
that I mean for someone like you an
experienced man who's you know who has
maybe commitment commitment possibly not
not on the legal angle book spiritually
to someone yes and who can who can be
trusted to to live that out you know
fully trust it I'm very very committed
to my partner yes I believe you I've
heard you speak of her very with great
affection and with great deal of with a
great deal of soul connection kind of
and I believe that but but everybody's
not you as we're talking about you know
we're talking about the 28 year old here
yeah so I mean some part of this and
this is I think something Jeff would
agree on I think we need to make
attachment theory and the understanding
of romantic relationships
we have to make that something of our
general education to people just like we
I mean think about how we've come to
realize that even certain aspects of
education border on being almost sacred
for us like we would find it odd if an
education system sort of forted people
ever gaining literacy or something like
that we would find that sort of deeply
deeply problematic I would hope that the
religion that's not a religion would
take very deeply from I try to argue for
this the fact that human cognition is
inherently dynamic inherently
developmental inherently trans jetsetter
a-- and therefore take very seriously
the the good science that Jeff and other
people point to about the relationship
the deep relationship between attachment
and romantic relationship and and they
would add to it there's the very good
work of Segal showing that your ability
for autumn apollo's going to love this
he's got to jump up at that when I say
this right that your capacity for
autobiographical narrative is predictive
of your ability to form an attachment
relationship with your children and so
getting people to be more conversant
with autobiographical narrative and with
fiction in general the fact that we have
reduced our culture's attention to
fiction and to the role think about how
Jordan Peterson is trying to bring back
a future offering as well right right
so I I would see that the religion
that's not a religion would take very
seriously all of this very good science
and then like Jordan has done and like
other people have done like Dan Siegel
has done and others would take very
seriously the project of again creating
a set of a dynamic system of psycho
technologies that is designed to afford
that and then and here's to your point
in particular that would bring with it
the idea that these psycho technologies
were as many psychos technology
do depend on very stable forms of
distributed cognition we can't for
example teach literacy to people unless
we set up this whole educational sort of
situation and machine that's running
societally you know you may
litter your own particular kind of
literacy for your kid just like it
that's kind of useless right in the end
right right and so I think I don't know
well I don't know if I would say
enforcement argue me because again
there's probably there's probably a
biological thing towards pair-bonding
just because it's the most manageable of
the marriage relationships but again I I
worry a little bit well more than a
little bit about being sort of
ethnocentric on this I mean you know for
example you know you have non-monogamous
relationships even the New Testament and
then you have Jesus also say except a
man you know leave his mother and father
right he can't follow me so even the
Bible's attitude towards family I think
is not a clear endorsement of monogamy
at least it seems that way to me
I mean you're probably more conversant
with the Bible than I am i do think that
committed you know committed long-term
relationships that are readily learn
about by children are central to giving
them this kind of education it might be
you might be able to make a case that
monogamy is the way to do that but that
needs a little bit more argument to my
mind but well I will agree on you where
is you do need committed relationships
and they need to have a structure that's
stable and readily learn about by a
small child and it puts that child in a
situation oh of course of course
so let me say back what I'm hearing you
say I think I'm hearing you say that
using cognitive science and some
psychological studies of how people get
attached to one another a lot of
psychological said a lot of
psychological research on that and
having a community of people who
understand that is going to produce a
situation where when when Jack and Sally
at age 28 decide that they're going to
pair up and form a family that there's
there's a solid community around them
that's gonna sort of hold their feet to
the fire to say you know so that one so
that one you know seven years later when
Jack is out with his buddies and you
know he's thinking about fooling around
with some woman one of them's gonna stop
them upside the head and say you know
your wife is at home you go home and
stop being a stop being an idiot you're
not a teenager anymore so I'm like that
you know what I'm saying yeah commitment
to pressure to because there's a
tremendous amount of centrifugal force
oh yeah on the family so there has to be
some sort of centripetal centripetal of
my sailing right fourth
to hold it together you know so I think
we a community before which they make
vows to one another yeah I do but I
think I not to sort of rain on anybody's
parade I think the the the practice the
the weddings we now have don't do any of
that because they're not bound to people
having to learn deeply about what it
means to raise a child and what it is to
be a child and what it is to be a parent
and again you know what are the deep
connections between attachment
relationships what are the things that
predict it and make it possible I've
often found it odd I hope people don't
jump on me for this so I'm I'm
expressing a thought here that we make
people get a license before they get a
car but we don't make them do any kind
of test before they have a child we take
we take it that well you can have sex
that's enough right to to become a
parent and why do we make I can't like
here's another important job being a
teacher my ability to speak is
insufficient I get well I can talk let
me be a teacher no no I have to do all
of this stuff because we realize no no
it's so important you're shaping a human
mind and I take that seriously or a
doctor well I'm just gonna help people
no no you have to go through all the
lists and you have to pass all these
tests because it's a it's a body and you
gotta take great care of it well parents
are shaping minds and taking care of our
bodies and yet we we we don't put I'm
not saying we have a government enforced
license I was using that as analogy but
why do we not have a culture that
requires people to commit to a serious
kind of education before they are
allowed to take seriously the prospect
of having a child that's what I'm
actually saying I know what I don't want
to legislate this okay no I do
understand and that's where I think we
people used to learn how to take care of
children by being part of large family
families exactly extended families yeah
I do think you know when I say about
monogamy
I'm not I'm not making attempting to
make a case for the nuclear family
mm-hmm which I think has been in many
ways very disastrous for our society I
think for one thing it does is it robs
women who wish to make their family the
center of their life as a career home
making it puts them into a situation of
tremendous loneliness ya know and and
also regardless of everything we say a
diminished social status so they go with
loneliness and a diminished social
status which of course you know is a
terrific corrosive to people's
self-esteem and their sense of efficacy
yeah and and let's be honest of course
the negative family has also led to
people being trapped because women
especially been trapped so you know
financially in nuclear families as well
which is deeply problematic you see this
is why you know I liked your
conversation with Jordan Hall so much
when he started saying as you're talking
he was going to the bigger structures
into the bigger structures into the
bigger structures right yeah that is the
problem every time every time we start
touching these things were it's like
we're pulling on a tapestry and
different threads and start coming guys
and that's why I'm grateful that you've
made the correction I'm not I don't have
the knowledge of the wisdom to found a
religion that's not what's going on here
what Jordan and I and others are doing
is to try and you know articulate and
helpful and hopefully enhance a process
that is already at work and maybe we
could we could close off there Mary I
don't wanna I don't want you can you can
say something more I'm not trying to hog
the final word on the conversation or
anything like that well I'm fine with
that I think we covered a lot of ground
I think we made some good progress and I
hope you enjoy my my latest video and of
course we will marry that goes with a
question I mean you you you you keep
doing work on my work I'm gonna keep
wanting to talk to you of course that
goes to what the point you just made
earlier in our in our discussion so I
will definitely load this on my channel
not sure when send me in an email any
links you'd like me to put in to like in
in the notes for the video like Mother's
Day links to your channel anything else
you want just send me an email of what
you want no make sure that gets in there
and so maybe I could close them because
I was the host by just thanking you and
I found this discussion of course always
with you I find it very it's highly
pleasurable highly insightful and I like
the fact that you bring to it a lot of
respect and care and affection so thank
you for that well thank you John it was
pleasure for sure okay
take care bye bye